- Hey everyone, this is Daniel for Rock the JVM
やあみんな、Rock the JVMのDanielだよ
and you are watching a tutorial
今回のチュートリアルは
on Scala metaprogramming basics with inlines.
Scalaメタプログラミングの基礎、inlineについてだ
So what is metaprogramming?
じゃあメタプログラミングって何か？
Metaprogramming means the ability to program
メタプログラミングっていうのは、プログラムを使って
with other programs.
他のプログラムを操作する能力のことだ
So code that manipulates other Scala code at compile time.
つまり、コンパイル時に他のScalaコードを操作するコードってことだね
Now, obviously I'll assume that you're familiar
もちろんScalaの基礎は知ってる前提で
with Scala basics, you won't need too much
進めるけど、このチュートリアルについていくのに
to follow this tutorial,
そんなに難しい知識は必要ないよ
but I will recommend you try this out for yourself.
ただ、自分で手を動かしてみることをおすすめするよ
I'll leave a link to the GitHub repository
GitHubリポジトリのリンクを
in the description and I'll also include
概要欄に貼っておくし
a written form on the blog on Rock the JVM.
Rock the JVMのブログにも記事を載せておくからね
Now this tutorial is standalone
このチュートリアルは単体でも完結してるし
and I recommend that you run this yourself,
自分で実行してみることをおすすめするけど
but it's part of a long form course on Scala 3 macros
これはScala 3マクロのフルコースの一部なんだ
and metaprogramming that I've just published.
メタプログラミングのコースを最近リリースしたばかりでね
So metaprogramming is easily the most magical feature set
メタプログラミングは間違いなくScalaの中で最も魔法みたいな機能で
of Scala that very few people understand
理解してる人はすごく少ないんだ
and many were looking to learn more about
もっと学びたいって人は多いんだけど
because documentation is pretty theoretical.
ドキュメントがかなり理論的だからね
So I made this course to cover pretty much everything
だからこのコースを作って、inline、マクロ、AST操作とか
you need to know about inlines, macros, AST manipulation,
必要なことをほぼ全部カバーしたんだ
pretty much all you need to be a master of metaprogramming.
メタプログラミングをマスターするのに必要なことは全部入ってるよ
We write thousands of lines of code in the course.
コースの中で数千行のコードを書くし
And we also have two real life projects to give you some real practice with metaprogramming.
実際のプロジェクトも2つあって、メタプログラミングの実践的な練習ができるようになってる
And by the end of this course, you should have all the skills of a senior developer to be able to write libraries
このコースを終える頃には、シニアデベロッパーとしてライブラリを書いたり
and tools and correctness checkers and various productivity improvements for your team.
ツールや正確性チェッカー、チームの生産性を上げる色々なものを作るスキルが身につくはずだ
So if you're interested in the subject, I recommend that you check it out.
興味がある人はぜひチェックしてみてね
I'm going to leave a link in the description.
リンクは概要欄に貼っておくよ
Now to this day, the power of Scala metaprogramming is at this point unmatched compared to other programming languages.
さて、現時点でScalaのメタプログラミングの力は他のプログラミング言語と比べて比類がないんだ
There are many languages that do offer metaprogramming capabilities, for example, Lisp, but they lose types.
メタプログラミング機能を持つ言語は色々あるよ、例えばLispとかね。でも型が失われるんだ
There are other languages that are strongly typed, but they only offer metaprogramming as text processors or compiler plugins.
強い型付けの言語もあるけど、メタプログラミングはテキストプロセッサやコンパイラプラグインとしてしか提供してない
But nobody offers the kind of well-typed macros and metaprogramming in the same language in the same compiler pipeline as Scala does.
でも、Scalaみたいに同じ言語で同じコンパイラパイプラインの中で型付きマクロとメタプログラミングを提供してる言語は他にないんだ
So I really encourage you to learn about macros and metaprogramming in general just for you to understand what is possible in a programming language.
だからマクロやメタプログラミングについて学ぶことを本当におすすめするよ。プログラミング言語で何ができるかを理解するためにもね
So, with that being said, let me go to the actual code itself.
じゃあ前置きはこのくらいにして、実際のコードに行こう
So I've just created a very basic Scala project, so here under buildSBT you can create your own Scala project.
すごくシンプルなScalaプロジェクトを作ったよ。ここのbuild.sbtを見て、自分でもScalaプロジェクトを作れるからね
I've just added a couple of Scala compiler options.
Scalaコンパイラのオプションをいくつか追加してある
One that is very important for us is this thing called -x print post inlining, which essentially prints the entire Scala code that will end up being compiled after inlining.
特に重要なのがこの-Xprint:postInliningっていうオプションで、インライン化の後にコンパイルされる最終的なScalaコード全体を出力してくれるんだ
So after the metaprogramming part, and this will tell us essentially what's happening in the compiler that we are going to demonstrate in this tutorial.
つまりメタプログラミングの処理後のコードで、このチュートリアルでデモするコンパイラの中身が分かるようになる
So we're going to focus our attention on this inline basic thing.
じゃあこのinlineの基本的なところに注目していこう
My object is called simple inlines.
objectの名前はSimpleInlinesだ
I might as well name my file that way.
ファイル名もそれに合わせておこう
So simple inlines.
SimpleInlinesと
Okay, and I'm going to collapse buildSBT in my file explorer and let's focus on inlines.
OK、build.sbtはファイルエクスプローラーで畳んで、inlineに集中しよう
All right, so if I start with a very simple function like increment.
じゃあまず、すごくシンプルなincrementっていう関数から始めよう
increment with an x that is an int, returns an int, and this is x plus one, let's say.
incrementはxがIntで、Intを返す。中身はx + 1としよう
If I have a val, let's call this a number, which is three.
valでaNumberを定義して、値は3にしよう
If I invoke this increment function, I'll obtain, obviously, the number four, so I'm going to have val four as increment a number.
このincrement関数を呼び出せば当然4が返ってくるから、val fourをincrement(aNumber)としよう
Now, let me check SPT output just for you to see what kind of output we should expect and the kind of tracking that we're going to do
じゃあsbtの出力を確認してみよう。どんな出力が期待されるか、そしてこれらの関数をinlineにした時の
when marking these functions inline.
変化をこれから追っていくからね
So let me go not save this file yet.
まだファイルは保存しないでおこう
I'm going to call SBT.
sbtを起動するよ
And in my SBT output, I'm going to hit tilde compile.
sbtの出力で~compileを実行する
And we're going to obtain essentially the final code that will be compiled after inline.
そうするとインライン化後にコンパイルされる最終的なコードが出てくるんだ
So currently we have this simple inline extends object and whatever, and we have, okay, just a basic object.
今のところSimpleInlinesがobjectを継承してて、まあ普通のobjectだね
Now, if I save this little file, simple inlines, we're going to essentially recompile everything.
じゃあこのSimpleInlinesファイルを保存すると、全部再コンパイルされる
And now we're going to have the method increment a number is three and val four is the invocation of this function comrack.jvm inline simple inlines increment on the a number variable.
するとincrementメソッドが出てきて、aNumberは3、val fourはcom.rockthejvm.inline.SimpleInlines.incrementをaNumber変数に対して呼び出してる
So this is the final code that will be compiled after processing or metaprogramming.
これがメタプログラミング処理後にコンパイルされる最終的なコードだ
So the way that scholar metaprogramming work is that everything that manipulates scholar code is going to essentially generate the final code that will be compiled.
Scalaのメタプログラミングの仕組みは、Scalaコードを操作するものは全て最終的にコンパイルされるコードを生成するってことなんだ
And then that code is essentially well typed scholar code that will be subject to the rest of the compiler pipeline.
そしてそのコードは型の整ったScalaコードで、残りのコンパイラパイプラインに渡されるんだよ
Okay, so we can make simple methods, obviously, we can call them like we do in a regular skull code, this is nothing rocket science.
OK、普通にメソッドを作って、普通のScalaコードみたいに呼び出せる。ここまでは何も難しくないよね
But if I can create a method increment, I'm going to call this inc with the same signature, but I'm going to mark it inline.
でもincrementメソッドを作ったように、今度はincっていう同じシグネチャのメソッドを作って、inlineを付けてみよう
Essentially, what inline does is it copies the implementation at the call site.
inlineがやることは基本的に、呼び出し元に実装をコピーすることなんだ
So if I say val four is instead of increment, we have inc on a number, if I save this, if I save this file, the val four here is copying a number,
つまりval fourをincrementの代わりにinc(aNumber)にして保存すると、val fourの中身はaNumberの値をコピーしてきて
or it's copying the implementation of x plus one, referring to x from wherever it was passed as an argument, which was the a number.
x + 1の実装をコピーしてる。xは引数として渡されたもの、つまりaNumberを参照してるんだ
So what we're going to obtain here in the output is the val four is the variable a number plus one.
だから出力で得られるのは、val fourがaNumber + 1という変数になる
So essentially, this compiles to or reduces to a number plus one at compile time.
つまり、これはコンパイル時にaNumber + 1にコンパイルされる、というか展開されるんだ
And the compile time thing is very important because inlines are surprisingly powerful tool for meta programming.
このコンパイル時っていうのがすごく重要で、inlineはメタプログラミングの驚くほど強力なツールなんだ
Now we can also inline the arguments to a function by passing them explicitly rather than evaluating them first before a function invocation.
さらに、引数を先に評価するんじゃなくて、そのまま展開してインライン化することもできるよ
So for example, if I have, let's call this product or result as inc on let's say two times a number plus one.
例えば、resultをinc(2 * aNumber + 1)としてみよう
So this is going to be two times three plus one plus one, that's going to be eight.
これは2 × 3 + 1 + 1で8になるね
And having written this expression, let's check what the compiler output says.
この式を書いたところで、コンパイラの出力を確認してみよう
So this generated the entire code again.
コード全体がまた生成されたね
This is not necessarily something that I'm interested in.
こっちの方は今は興味ないんだけど
Okay.
OK
So look at this.
これを見て
We have the value eight saying the val proxy, which is two times a number plus one, and then we have this thing plus one.
8の値のところで、val proxyが2 * aNumber + 1で、その後にproxy + 1ってなってる
So this reduces to, so this reduces to the little block of code saying val, let's call this proxy as two times a number plus one.
つまりこれは、val proxy = 2 * aNumber + 1っていうコードブロックに展開されるんだ
And then we have proxy plus one, and then we have proxy plus one.
そしてproxy + 1になると。proxy + 1だね
This is what the code says.
これがコードの中身だ
So we have an intermediate variable and then we're doing this proxy plus one.
中間変数があって、それからproxy + 1をやってるんだ
Now, with a feature called inline arguments, we can define a little method.
ここで、inline引数っていう機能を使うと、ちょっとしたメソッドを定義できる
Let's call this inline function.
これをinline関数と呼ぼう
And I'm going to call this inc with inline arguments.
incIAって名前にする。inline引数付きのincだ
So inc with inline arguments, I'm going to have inline x as an int.
incIAはinline xをIntとして受け取る
I'm going to return x plus one.
そしてx + 1を返す
Well, in this case, val eight version two as inc ia with two times a number plus one.
この場合、val eightV2 = incIA(2 * aNumber + 1)とすると
In this case, it inlines where it expands the variable without evaluating it first directly in the method call.
引数を先に評価せずに、メソッド呼び出しの中で直接展開するんだ
So this should reduce to, so reduces to two times a number plus one, which is the argument, plus one, which is the implementation.
つまりこれは、2 * aNumber + 1（これが引数）+ 1（これが実装）に展開される
So this is going to be the final expression that this will generate.
これが生成される最終的な式だよ
So as I'm saving the file, let me scroll down.
ファイルを保存したら、下にスクロールしてみよう
So look at this.
これを見て
The final version two is two times a number plus one, which is the argument, and then plus one, which is from the method body.
最終的なv2は、2 * aNumber + 1が引数で、+ 1がメソッド本体からのものだ
So arguments can also be expanded exactly as they are without having to be computed first.
つまり引数は先に計算されずに、そのまま展開されるんだ
Now, the interesting thing is that whenever the compiler sees the argument in the method body, it will simply expand that to whatever the expression was that we passed in the method invocation, which is very similar conceptually.
面白いのは、コンパイラがメソッド本体の中で引数を見つけると、メソッド呼び出しで渡された式をそのまま展開するっていうこと。概念的には名前渡しに似てるんだ
So conceptually, similar to a by name invocation.
概念的には名前渡し呼び出しに似てるんだけど
But this is done at compile time directly.
でもこれはコンパイル時に直接行われる
So these are expanded within the method body.
つまり、メソッド本体の中で展開されるんだ
And only inline methods can have inline arguments.
それとinline引数はinlineメソッドでしか使えないよ
So again, inline arguments are expanded directly wherever the argument is being used.
もう一度言うと、inline引数は引数が使われてる場所で直接展開される
And if you use them multiple times, it will be expanded multiple times.
複数回使えば、複数回展開されるんだ
So if I save this file, and I check the compiling difference.
ファイルを保存して、コンパイル結果の違いを確認しよう
Look at this.
これを見て
We have two times this sucker plus two times this sucker plus one.
2 * こいつ + 2 * こいつ + 1ってなってるね
Okay.
OK
So every time you have the argument, it will be expanded or it will be inlined.
引数がある度に、展開される、つまりインライン化されるんだ
The difference between inline argument and the by name invocation is that this is done at compile time.
inline引数と名前渡しの違いは、これがコンパイル時に行われるってことだ
So only that the args are expanded at compile time.
引数がコンパイル時に展開されるっていうだけの違いなんだ
So this fact of the expansion at compile time is super, super, super important.
このコンパイル時の展開っていう事実が、もう超超超重要なんだ
And this will allow us to do metaprogramming with the kind of techniques that I'm going to show you throughout the rest of this course.
そしてこれが、このコースの残りで紹介していくテクニックでメタプログラミングを可能にしてくれる
Now a practical direct implication of using inlines aside from the kind of information that's being serviced at compile time is that inlines can be used for performance optimization.
inlineのコンパイル時情報以外の直接的な実用面として、inlineはパフォーマンス最適化にも使えるんだ
Because instead of method calls, you have the method body directly injected into the code.
メソッド呼び出しの代わりに、メソッド本体が直接コードに注入されるからね
And I can give you a quick example for that.
ちょっとした例を見せるよ
So let me define a method test inline.
testInlineっていうメソッドを定義しよう
And I'm going to replicate an example that I just saw on the internet a couple of days ago, where people were bragging that JavaScript is fast.
数日前にネットで見た例を再現するよ。JavaScriptが速いって自慢してる人がいたんだけど
Well, within lines, you can write pretty darn fast Scala code on the JVM.
inlineを使えば、JVM上でめちゃくちゃ速いScalaコードが書けるんだよ
So I'm going to replicate a little for loop or a double for loop.
forループ、正確には二重forループを再現してみよう
So people used to have like an array, so array of like 10,000 elements, and then it would have a 4i from 0 to the length of the array.
10,000要素の配列があって、iを0から配列の長さまで回すんだ
So from one to 10,000, so they will do a double for loop.
1から10,000まで。二重forループだよ
So for J as 0 to 10k, they would do something like array of i plus equals a random constant.
jを0から10,000まで回して、array(i) += 適当な定数をやる
And out of this would have array of i plus equals another random constant.
そしてその外側でもarray(i) += 別の定数をやる
And they would measure the time it takes for something like this to happen on various languages.
これを色んな言語でどれくらい時間がかかるか測ってたんだ
And Python was surprisingly slow and whatever.
Pythonが意外と遅かったりとかね
But I wanted to give you a little demonstration of how this looks like for regular Scala code versus inline Scala code.
でも普通のScalaコードとinline版のScalaコードでどう違うか見せたかったんだ
So I'm going to replicate a little for loop via a little method.
小さなメソッドでforループを再現するよ
So I'm going to say loop with an, so I'm going to have an inline, inline def loop with a little type parameter.
inline def loopを定義する。型パラメータ付きのinlineメソッドだ
Let's say inline start as an A, inline condition with a boolean and inline advance as A to A.
inline startをA型、inline conditionでBoolean、inline advanceでA => Aと
So just to replicate a regular C style for loop and also an inline body or an inline action as A to anything.
C言語スタイルのforループを再現するために、inline bodyというかinline actionをA => 何でも良い、としよう
Okay.
OK
And I'm going to write variables here.
ここでvarを使うよ
So I'm going to say var A start and then I'm going to say while condition on A.
var a = startとして、while(condition(a))で回す
I'm going to say action on A and then I'm going to advance.
action(a)を実行して、それからadvanceする
So A is equal to advance on A.
a = advance(a)だね
So this is essentially me replicating a for loop in Scala.
これで要するにScalaでforループを再現してるんだ
Okay.
OK
And I'm using variables and while loops.
varとwhileループを使ってる
And if you're at this course, I'm pretty sure you're not dogmatic about this.
このコースを受けてるなら、この辺は柔軟に考えてくれると思う
Variables and while loops are really powerful if you want to write really performant code.
varとwhileループは高速なコードを書くのにすごく強力なんだ
So I'm going to have this inline def loop and I'm going to replicate this sucker.
このinline def loopを使って、さっきの処理を再現するよ
So I'm going to have a val start as let's say system current time millis just to measure time.
val start = System.currentTimeMillis()で時間を測る
So I'm going to call this start.
これをstartとしよう
Then I'm going to have a value of R, which is a random number.
そしてランダムな値のvalをrとして
I'm going to say random next int, let's say 10,000 and I'm going to create another one.
Random.nextInt(10000)にして、もう一つ作ろう
I'm going to call this U and then I'm going to run a quote unquote for loop,
これをuとして、いわゆるforループを実行する
which is my loop function.
さっきのloop関数を使うよ
So I'm going to say loop starting at zero, the condition is thing is less than 10,000.
loop、開始値は0で、条件は _ < 10000
And then I'm going to say underscore plus one.
そして _ + 1で進める
So it's like a for loop in Java, but this is a function with multiple argument lists.
Javaのforループみたいだけど、複数の引数リストを持つ関数だ
So I'm going to say I and I'm going to have another loop with zero and then a hundred thousand.
iとして、その中にまたloopで0から100,000まで
So underscore is less than a hundred thousand and underscore plus one and given a J inside.
_ < 100000と _ + 1で、jとして内側の処理を書く
Okay, then I'm going to write an array.
そしたら配列に書き込む
Let me define the array.
配列を定義しよう
So val array as array dot of dim of type integer.
val array = Array.ofDim[Int]で
I'm going to have 10,000 numbers.
10,000個の数値を持たせる
I'm going to say array of I is equal to array of I plus Q.
array(i) = array(i) + uとする
And finally, after the first loop, I'm going to say array of I is equal to array of I plus this other random variable, which is R.
最後に、最初のループの後でarray(i) = array(i) + rっていうもう一つのランダム変数を足す
So then I'm going to have a print line.
そしてprintlnで出力する
So print line, I'm going to say inline version and I'm going to inject a little expression here.
printlnで「inline version」と書いて、式を入れる
So I'm going to have a system current time millis minus the start divided by 1000.
System.currentTimeMillis() - startを1000で割る
So this is an expression.
これが式だ
I'm going to divide this by 1000 point zero.
1000.0で割って
So this is going to be the number of seconds.
秒数にする
Okay.
OK
So this is going to be my little for loop.
これが僕のforループだ
But this is going to be the inline version.
でもこれはinline版だね
And I'm also going to use a null inline version.
inlineなし版も作ろう
So I'm going to copy this.
これをコピーして
I'm going to call this test and no inline.
testNoInlineって名前にする
I'm going to cut out all the inlines from the function definition.
関数定義からinlineを全部取り除くよ
So this loop is just a regular function with a bunch of parameters.
このloopはただのパラメータがいっぱいある普通の関数だ
Nothing is inline.
何もinlineじゃない
And I'm going to say no inline version.
こっちは「no inline version」って表示する
Okay.
OK
And I'm going to type in a main.
そしてmainメソッドを書こう
So main with args as array string.
mainでargsはArray[String]として
And this is going to be a test inline and then test no inline.
testInline()してからtestNoInline()を実行する
That's it.
これだけだ
So this is going to be my little application.
これが僕の小さなアプリケーションだ
And in another terminal, I'm going to start another SBT.
別のターミナルでもう一つsbtを起動するよ
Okay.
OK
And then I'm going to say run main.
runMainを実行する
And then I'm going to say comrack.jvm.
com.rockthejvmの
And I have simple inlines.
SimpleInlinesだ
Comrack.jvm.
com.rockthejvm
Inline simple inlines.
inline.SimpleInlines
Okay.
OK
So inline version is 0.1 second.
inline版は0.1秒だ
No inline version is 1.5 seconds.
inlineなし版は1.5秒
So like 15 times performance improvement just by adding inlines.
inlineを付けるだけで15倍のパフォーマンス改善だよ
And it actually makes sense because in the double for loop,
これは当然で、二重forループの中で
we don't have function calls,
関数呼び出しがなくて
but rather we have while loops.
代わりにwhileループになってるからなんだ
So no function calls and no indirection.
関数呼び出しもインダイレクションもない
And that causes all this extra overhead.
その余分なオーバーヘッドが全部なくなるんだ
So inlines can help with performance improvement.
というわけで、inlineはパフォーマンス改善に役立つ
But the place where we're going to spend most of our time is in the information
でも僕らが一番時間を使うのは、inlineがコンパイル時に
that the inline surface to the compile time for metaprogramming.
メタプログラミングのために提供する情報の方だ
Okay.
OK
So this is one of the main reasons why I am going to focus on inlines
だからinlineに注目するんだ
and also macros in the beginning of the next chapter.
次の章の最初ではマクロにも触れるよ
So I just wanted to add performance optimization here because it's obvious
パフォーマンス最適化の話を入れたのは、明白な効果があるからで
and because it's also an important outcome of using inlines.
inlineを使う重要な結果の一つだからなんだ
Now the final feature of inlines that I wanted to show you in this video is transparent inlines.
さて、この動画で見せたいinlineの最後の機能はtransparent inlineだ
And transparent inlines means that the most concrete type definition of a function is going to be surfaced to the compiler
transparent inlineっていうのは、関数の最も具体的な型定義がコンパイラに公開されるってことだ
because the compiler has access to those concrete times at compile time.
コンパイラがコンパイル時にその具体的な型にアクセスできるからなんだ
Let me show you what I mean.
何のことか見せるね
So I'm going to have an inline function.
inline関数を作ろう
So an inline def, let's call this wrap, that takes an item as an int and this returns an option int.
inline defでwrapっていう関数。itemをIntで受け取って、Option[Int]を返す
Okay.
OK
And then I'm going to return a sum.
そしてSomeを返すよ
So look at this.
ここに注目して
We are declaring that this function returns an int, but it actually returns a more concrete type than option.
この関数はOption[Int]を返すと宣言してるけど、実際にはOptionよりも具体的な型を返してる
It returns a subtype of option.
Optionのサブタイプを返してるんだ
Now, if I define a vowel, let's call this an option as option int as wrap with the number seven.
ここでvalを定義して、anOptionをOption[Int]としてwrap(7)を呼び出すと
Obviously that's correct because the option int conforms to the type signature of this method.
もちろんこれは正しい。Option[Int]はこのメソッドの型シグネチャに適合してるからね
And obviously this compiles and the type checker is okay.
当然コンパイルは通るし、型チェッカーもOKだ
Now, if I prefix this definition with a keyword transparent, what the transparent method does is that depending on the number that you pass inside
さて、この定義にtransparentキーワードを付けると、渡す値や
or depending on the compile time information that the body of the method gives to the compiler,
メソッド本体がコンパイラに与えるコンパイル時情報に応じて
I can use more concrete types than the one declared in the function signature.
関数シグネチャで宣言されてるより具体的な型を使えるようになるんだ
So with the transparent keyword, I should be able to say val a sum, which is a sum int, and I'm going to say wrap seven.
transparentキーワードを付ければ、val aSome: Some[Int] = wrap(7)って書けるようになる
And this is also okay.
これもOKだ
But it's also okay only in the context of transparent.
でもこれがOKなのはtransparentの場合だけだよ
If I cut this out and I save this, wrap seven is not okay because wrap seven declares to be an option int and the implementation is opaque to the compiler.
transparentを外して保存すると、wrap(7)はダメになる。wrap(7)はOption[Int]を返すと宣言されてて、実装がコンパイラから見えなくなるからね
But otherwise, if the expression of the function is transparent to the compiler, then the type, the most concrete type of this expression can be used by the compiler to do some extra type checks.
でも関数の式がコンパイラに対してtransparentなら、その式の最も具体的な型をコンパイラが使って追加の型チェックができるんだ
So this is also okay only if transparent.
だからこれはtransparentの場合だけOKなんだ
So you can see here that some methods can be declared transparent and even have the type signature any or whatever very general type,
つまり、メソッドをtransparentとして宣言すれば、型シグネチャがAnyとかすごく一般的な型でも
but the compiler can have access to the concrete method implementation.
コンパイラは具体的なメソッド実装にアクセスできるんだ
And that expression can give much more information than just the signature of the method, thereby allowing the compiler to do more rigorous type checks than by just looking at the type signature.
そしてその式はメソッドのシグネチャだけよりもはるかに多くの情報を提供して、コンパイラがより厳密な型チェックをできるようになる
All right, folks, this was an introduction to inlines in Scala.
さあ、みんな。これがScalaのinline入門だったよ
I hope I stimulated your appetite for metaprogramming.
メタプログラミングへの食欲を刺激できたなら嬉しいな
And if so, check out the long form course on Scala 3 macros and metaprogramming that I've just launched.
もしそうなら、リリースしたばかりのScala 3マクロとメタプログラミングのフルコースをチェックしてね
I think you'll enjoy it.
きっと楽しめると思うよ
And until next time, this was Daniel for Rock the JVM signing off.
じゃあまた次回。Rock the JVMのDanielでした、またね